Abraham: Hi I’m Abraham
Nicole: and I’m Nicole
and throughout this course we
will be talking to you about
different aspects of cyber security
Abraham: In these introductory videos we
will look at the concept of cyber security
and why it is important everywhere.
The core function of cyber security is
to protect our systems, networks and
devices and the services we access both
online and in our place of work, keeping
them safe from digital surveillance,
theft, or damage, known as cybercrime.
Nicole: The use of new technologies
and the internet has given criminals
a new tool for committing crime
which can subsequently take place
'virtually' anywhere in the world.
Cyber crime is increasing all the
time and is becoming more complex
affecting essential services,
companies and individuals whilst
also threatening national security.
So why is cyber security so important?
Abraham: Nearly everything we do today
involves using smart phones, computers
and the internet and it’s hard to
see how we can function without them.
Online banking, shopping, ordering
an Uber or a pizza, we put our
information out there hoping it is
safe from cyber criminals that may
use it for their nefarious activities!
But how can you be sure it is safe?
Nicole: Just think about this for
a minute, would you leave your
most valuable possessions on show
for anyone to see or pick up?
Well, it is the same for your data!
We are all at risk of having our
personal information stolen by cyber
criminals to sell on to others, create
false identities, or to use it to con
us into giving out more information.
So what are the key
concepts of Cyber security?
Abraham:
Confidentiality…Integrity…Availability…Authentication.
Confidentiality means controlling access
levels of data and sensitive information.
It should only be available to those who
have right to view, store or transmit
it, and if someone doesn’t need to
know, then they shouldn’t have access.
Integrity means that all information
is maintained safely as it
should be with no modifications.
Sensitive data should not be tampered
with or compromised by any means.
Nicole: Availability means that sensitive
information and data should not be readily
available but should be accessible to
those who have the appropriate authority
at a time the time they need it.
Abraham: Authentication- means controls
need to be in place to authenticate
the identity of users and that access
is given to the appropriate people.
To help to make this more secure
multifactor authentication should be used.
Nicole: We often talk about
risk but what is risk?
In simple terms risk means
something bad happening.
In terms of cyber security, risk
is the potential for loss, damage
or destruction of assets or data.
Risk can be affected by a vulnerability,
which is a weakness that can create
exposure to a threat or a hazard.
Having adequate cyber security
can help can minimise that risk.
Abraham: Hazards are the
probability of an occurrence of
something potentially damaging.
Threats show more intent and
are more likely to harm and
vulnerability is how susceptible
you are to that hazard or threat.
Nicole: So, there you are the basic
concept of cyber security, but don’t
worry if it seems a bit confusing,
as you progress through this course
you will look at these and other
terms in more detail and get a full
understanding of Cyber Security practices.